He's been inducted into the marketing
hall of fame. He's the mind behind
modern classics like Purple Cow, Tribes,
Lynchpin, The Dip, This Is Marketing,
This Is Strategy, and so many more. The
kind of books that you don't just read,
they get underlined, quoted in
boardrooms, and echoed by creators
everywhere. He's the author of 21
bestselling books translated into more
than 35 languages and he spent decades
helping people see the world and their
work a little differently. Please
welcome Seth Goden.
>> Thank you for being here, Seth. Really
appreciate it.
>> What a treat. It's really fun to talk to
both of you.
>> I Well, we're ready for an amazing
amazing journey and story together. Um,
we as podcasters are now doing this in
the physical world. Um, because we're
primarily in the digital world, but
every time that Shannon and I start a
story, a new story, we always try to
start something a little bit different
than most, a little bit more uh,
research driven or creative. So, we're
going to throw you with this one. In
1994, you published the information
please business almanac, a kind of pre-
internet attempt to organize useful
useful knowledge long before Google or
chat GPT ever existed. If you were to
write that book today in an age where AI
can index almost everything, how would
how would it read and would you say
tools like chat dbt are fulfilling that
mission or breaking it?
>> It's a great place to start. So the
almanac was the culmination of my work
as a book packager. Book packagers
invent ideas, bring them to publishers,
books that are too hard for any single
person to make. So it was seven people
working together for nine months to make
an 800page researched book filled with
tables and charts and articles. And it
was going to be my life's work. I would
have a new edition every year forever.
And a year and a half after it came out,
uh, the internet showed up and it became
worthless. It was still something I was
glad I made. It was needed to have this
thing on your desk. It was, for example,
we had the number for the Hawaii Public
Library because if you're working late
in New York, you could call Hawaii and
still get an answer to your question
because they were open, right? Um, so
what would it say today? It would be one
sheet of paper, [laughter] right? Look
it up your damn self at the end. And
that's I think the thing that people
don't understand yet about uh LLMs and
AI.
>> It's a little bit like a talking dog. If
you run into a talking dog, you
shouldn't believe everything it says,
but you also shouldn't dismiss it as a
novelty because it's a talking dog,
right? And what a lot of people are
doing is showing up with AI and saying,
"Here are my problems. Solve them."
they're giving it all their work away.
Don't do that. Give AI tasks and you do
projects
>> that when you have this assistant who
works basically for free all the time
for you,
>> you can go so much faster if you're
willing to do the scary work, but you
can't outsource the scary work because
if you do that, you got nothing left.
>> Couldn't agree more. I I think this is a
perfect segue to the first official
question uh which is and I think we
could all agree that regardless of AI
it's all about storytelling and we'd
like to take this conversation uh to a
journey more specifically about your two
most recent books this is marketing and
this is strategy so let's set the tone
today's topic and the entire purpose of
this wonderful event is AI in a recent
interview to describe AI like the
weather so today an amazing beautiful
day here in Philadelphia Pennsylvania
said, "What is the weather?"
>> You know, I learned a long time ago you
shouldn't judge a day by the weather
because you're giving away your agency.
We're not on Saturn. We're not on
Jupiter. We live in a world where we can
survive or maybe even thrive. And every
day has something wrong with it. Every
day has a defect that you can say,
"Well, I'm going to have to wait for
perfect." But if we wait for perfect,
we're going to be waiting a very long
time. So, we have today, this moment.
What are we going to do with it? How can
we focus on possibility and not try to
let ourselves off the hook? So, today in
Philadelphia, and it's so cool to be
with you two in person. Yeah, it's sunny
and you can walk outside and you have a
chance to make things better. So, why
not?
>> I love it. So, we're going to start uh
with this is marketing uh and then we're
going to gradually uh go to this is
strategy. Um you went from I believe one
hour a day to true creativity uh to
seven with AI. Um what specific
constraints did AI remove that unlock
the extra six hours? So think about all
the tasks you do every day. All the
meetings you have to go to, emails you
have to answer, pencils you have to
sharpen, all the stuff. These tasks
can consume us. Many people I know do
nothing but tasks all day long. What did
you do today? Well, I cleared my email
box. I went to these meetings. I
sharpened these pencils. I filled out
the spreadsheet. I went to work. But
that's not what we make anymore. We make
change. If you're not making a change
happen, why did you show up? What is a
marketer doing if they're not making a
change happen? They're just entertaining
us. Why? Right? Marketing exists to make
a change happen. So if that's the case
and you have this squadron of uh AI
workers ready to help you and you have a
partner in the sense that something like
Claude can encourage you, you can get
rid of all the tasks. So now I can't say
I had a really productive day if I was
only creative for an hour because when
I'm creative for an hour that's 45
minutes more than most people because I
don't have meetings and I don't have a
team. It's just me. But now because all
my tasks are done by an AI,
I better be creative for 7 hours or I've
just wasted a day.
>> Yeah.
>> How do you stay creative for seven
hours? Because I think a lot of people
have a difficulty with um
grappling with the idea that creativity
has like a halt sometimes.
>> Exactly.
>> So, how do you what what inspires you to
be able to keep going for that many
hours of the day? So let's talk about
creativity and let's talk about
attachment. What is creativity for? What
is innovation for? It's to solve a
problem that uh if you have a lock
without a key, it's not worth very much.
But if you have a pile of keys, they're
worth zero because if you don't have a
problem you can open with them while you
even have them. So, it's very easy to
get attached to the idea that creative
work isn't worth trying unless we're
sure it's going to work.
>> This is called attachment. I'm not
willing to do this unless I know it's
going to work. So, I become very focused
on the outcome. But if we become focused
on the outcome, we give up our practice.
We give up our process.
One way to think about attachment is
this. Let's say you and I want to swim
across a lake. The safe thing for us to
do would be for us to stay about five or
six feet apart and swim. And if one of
us gets into trouble, the other one
could help. The foolish thing would be
for me to tie one rope to your arm,
another rope, four ropes, four arms and
legs. We're attached. If we do that,
we're going to die, right? Because when
we seek to get attached to this outcome,
we take our eyes off what it actually is
to be creative. So I was fortunate over
the years to build up this muscle that
says this might not work. I say it to
myself all the time. So many
organizations have trouble saying that.
If you went to client meetings and began
your pitch with this might not work,
your pitches wouldn't go very well. You
need to be able to say this is going to
work, right? No, that's not where
creativity lies. Creativity lies in this
is worth trying, but it might not work.
>> Yeah.
>> And so every day I just get to do that
because sometimes the outcomes are fine
and they pay for me to do it again, but
I'm not attached.
>> Yeah.
So when when it comes to the marketing,
I think we could all agree storytelling
is is pre prevalent in in order to
separate yourself from your competition.
But if we can kind of go relatively
elementary,
what actually is good marketing? Or at
least what is it to you?
>> Well, I get to decide because I'm in the
marketing office. [laughter]
Uh
>> the king of marketing.
>> Marketing is not hype. It's not hustle.
It's not lying. And it's not even
promotion. We have words for all of
those things. Those words are not
marketing. I just told you what those
words were. Marketing is telling a true
story to people who want to hear it that
helps them get to where they want to go.
In order to do that, you have to build
the story. The product has to match,
right? So when Volkswagen uh decides to
defraud millions of people by faking the
emissions of their diesel things to to
fool the government, that was a
marketing choice
>> and it cost them billions of dollars
because no longer could they tell a true
story about what they were selling. They
decided not to do that.
>> And so if you say, "I got to get the
word out." Well, you've already made
your first mistake. Marketing is not
getting the word out. Marketing is
making something that people would miss
if they were gone. If it were gone and
that they want to tell the others you
don't get the word out, they get the
word out. [clears throat]
>> How do you make, you know, how do you do
that? Right? Because, and I'll just
speak for example, you know, we can go
on chat GBT or any other of the AI and
say, "Hey, tell me what to say in my
social media post for the next 30 days."
And you can obtain relatively decent
content, right? But
sometimes it doesn't come off as genuine
as as you'd want. Is is that necessarily
a bad thing or do you feel like more
people should should try something a
different potentially a different
approach to be able to have that
authentic voice when you're speaking?
>> All right, we're going to break this
into pieces because you said a hot
button word for me. We'll start with
that. [laughter]
Authenticity is a croc. People do not
want you to be authentic.
>> They want you to be consistent. If we go
to a surgeon and that surgeon had a
really really bad night's sleep and was
having a bad day, we don't want them to
authentically do a bad job of surgery,
right? That's not why we went.
>> Fair point.
>> We want professionals to be consistent.
>> So, social media turns this upside down
because every once in a while somebody
in Amy Winehouse character is
authentically disastrous and it draws a
crowd. So, we've now decided that the
way to be successful in social media is
to put on a show. Yeah. and to, you
know, bury your soul and whatever and it
breaks people. Don't do this. That's not
what professionals do. Instead, say, "My
goal is not the biggest possible social
media following. It's the right people,
and I'm going to make a promise to these
people about what they get from me, and
the purpose of this work is to create
enough tension for change to happen. I'm
not an unpaid employee of Mark
Zuckerberg. Instead, I'm here for a
reason. And the reason is to create the
conditions for you to decide that your
life would be better if you transact
>> with my brand, with me.
>> Yeah.
>> If within those constraints,
Claude or Chat GBT can write all your
posts. Fine. That's right. Every author
I know uses a spell check. Does that
mean they're cheating? Spell checks AI.
So, yeah, fine. Because we're not here
to understand the true Jonathan. We're
here to engage with the version of
Jonathan that we know and care about.
But that doesn't mean we know you. We
know your avatar.
>> But what about the hook? Because I think
for from me, and maybe you might agree,
uh there's so much good content that we
get consumed by it. Hence why the
scrolling world exists. But then when
you like something from someone, to me,
I feel like a lot of people drop off at
the at the at the sale, you know, hey,
uh, sign up for a newsletter or sign up
for a, um,
>> you know, a $1,000 ticket uh, in order
to be a part of this mentorship program
or or I always feel like that that is
the disingenuous part uh is is the is
the catch or is the call to action. Do
you have any opinions or thoughts on
that?
When people buy from you, you're not
asking them to do you a favor. You're
offering them a favor. If that's not
true, then you don't really understand
what you are marketing.
>> So, let's say uh I have a a falconry
facility in Gan, New York, where you can
actually uh get a Hawk and fly it. Now,
that's not free. That costs $400. It's
lifechanging, and you can go do it. Does
everyone want to go do this? Can
everyone afford to do this? Of course
not. So if on social media I'm posting
pictures of the Screech Owl and I'm
posting pictures of the Gossling Hawk
and I'm posting pictures of the Paragan.
Fine. Some people are going to watch
that because it's free TV, but some
people are going to say I need to be in
that spot. And then I can say, okay,
>> I will do you a favor and I will
exchange $400 for a chance for you to
join me here. and we're only open these
windows of time and when it's full, it's
full. So, I've created tension because
now you know you had the chance to do
this. You know that not everyone gets to
do this. You know that you could afford
it if you wanted to. Do you want to
come? There's no challenge here because
all the people who don't want to come,
great. Thanks for considering it. All
the people who do want to come, we're
meeting at 9:00 a.m. The end. Right? So,
where we get into trouble is when we
make average stuff for average people.
>> When we say, "You can pick anyone and
I'm anyone. Please, please, I worked
very hard. Come buy something from me."
>> That's not what we're in the business of
doing. We make souvenirs of our story.
If someone wants to buy the souvenir,
they buy the souvenir, but we don't have
to hustle for them to buy it.
>> Yeah. I
>> Oh, go ahead. Well, um, with the
explanation that you just had with
finding that group that you want to
market to that you should niche down to,
if
>> don't say down,
>> niche [laughter] up,
>> niche up, you correct.
>> Um, how do you find that without being
authentically yourself? Because if that
is your personal brand is being you,
then how do you find the right people if
you're not being genuine all the time? I
think it's a real mistake for your
personal brand to be you
>> because if your personal brand is you
and someone rejects it, that hurts. They
saw you and they don't like you, right?
You're playing a role. Paul McCartney is
playing a role. I am playing a role. I
don't talk like this at breakfast,
right? I am consistent in this role. And
I don't think I'm a fraud. In fact, I
think I'm the opposite because I'm
consistent. If you read a Seth Goden
blog post, yes, I wrote it myself, but
it just needs to sound like a Seth Goden
blog post. That's what makes it real.
And so showing up in the world, whether
you're AT&T or a soloreneur,
is about making a promise and keeping
it. And where we get really frustrated
is when the promise is clearly
fraudulent. When they say one thing and
do another. When we look behind the the
Gerber baby food factory and we see that
they're putting other stuff in. It might
even be not poisonous, but they said
that they were pure and and then they're
not. That's a different sort of
authenticity. That's consistency or not
delivering on that. So I think the trap
of social media which should be avoided
by most people is we got seduced and
indoctrinated into thinking first step
be famous, second step ask for a favor,
third step people send you money if
you're authentic enough.
None of those three steps make any sense
to me.
>> Yeah, 100%. Well, how then do you find
that person that you want to be?
>> Exactly. Right. So I call this the
smallest viable audience, not the
biggest possible audience. Now it could
be a very very large number of people.
The number of people in Patagonia's
smallest viable audience is 10 million.
Number of people who have bought a book
from me in the United States is 3
million. That means and none of them
none none of my books have sold three
million copies. That means to a rounding
error my market share in the United
States is zero. That's fine. It's
enough. Right? So when we're inventing
the product, right? Let's say we're
we're we're building a a digital
platform for that replaces agencies or
we're building a platform say if we
could pick any customers we wanted just
10 who would they be can we imagine them
even by name what do they like what
don't they like and ignore everybody
else shun the non-believers if you make
something for the smallest viable
audience that is so irresistible and so
remarkable that they talk about it your
problems are solved but if you try to
make average stuff for average people,
you're always going to be struggling.
>> I think there's a a pretty nice segue
into the strategy piece because I think
that's where it kind of comes in because
um selfishly speaking when when I
started my career, it was like, well,
everybody needs this and then everybody
really doesn't need it,
>> right?
>> I think they need it and therefore I
should market to every single person. So
I think maybe you can kind of speak to
the strategy piece because and why do we
why do you think we as a culture and a
society are consist consistently wanting
to to appease everyone, right? So
systems are real and we can talk about
systems for a bunch, but it begins with
the indoctrination of school. school was
invented by industrialists because they
were worried that they would run out of
obedient compliant factory workers and
it's based on the Prussian paramilitary
education system of the late 1800s. And
we built it on purpose. You process
people for a year. If they're defective,
you move them back and reprocess them.
If not, you graduate them to the next
thing. We give them tests. We mark the
tests. We standardize all the stuff.
What's the worst thing that could happen
to you? You fail. What's the worst thing
that happens to you is someone in power
criticizes you. That then we set all
these, you know, hormone-filled
15-year-olds free in the cafeteria and
now social pressure kicks in. You have
to wear exactly the right clothes for
this group to like you. And if you get
criticized or made fun of, all these bad
things happen. So we by the time a kid
is 18 years old, it's deep inside of
them. That that's how you succeed.
>> That it's very easy to seduce an author
into reading their reviews on Amazon,
which makes no sense. They're not going
to write that book again. Why do they
need to know what someone thought? A
one-star review and great authors,
right? Way better than me. Fcott
Fitzgerald, plenty of one-star reviews.
That doesn't mean it's a bad book. It
means the person who wrote the review
said, "This is not for me."
>> That gives the author no information
whatsoever. Right? It's not for me.
Okay, I get it. And people who speak
Italian, if you buy the US edition, the
English edition, it's not for you. I get
it. So, what we've got to do as
professionals
is eagerly send prospects to our
competition to be able to say, you walk
into a Ferrari dealership and you say,
"Look, I got five kids. I got to do
carpool." And you don't try to persuade
them to buy an Enzo, right? They say,
"Well, the kids can all sit on each
other's laps." You say, "My
brother-in-law has a Volvo dealership.
It's right down the street." That's a
generous thing to do. Send them to
someone who can help them. But if you're
not qualifying your customers, if you're
not qualifying them and saying, "This
isn't for you, then you're not a
professional."
to to speak on that qualifying. Um I
think people get that wrong most most
times or at least make it more difficult
than what it actually is. Um a
conversation I had the other day it was
like well I I have a product I have an
idea but I don't necessarily know the
product fit. How how do you actually
qualify?
I think you have to start in the other
direction. Who's it for is the first
question. The second question is what's
it for? Don't start with what's it for.
Start with who's it for? The person who
has this problem, right? The the the
legend of OXO, the the person who was
the brains behind it was suffering, I
think, from arthritis. And she persuaded
her husband to start this company. She
said, "Look, there are a lot of people
who are having trouble opening cans and
opening bottles. That's who it's for.
What's it for? Make something that's
beautifully designed that helps them
that other people who don't have that
problem will also want to buy." Now we
know the who's it for. Now we know the
what's it for. And if someone says I
want a 39 cent can opener, we say this
one's not for you. Go down over there.
They sell cheap ones. This is a can
opener worth paying for.
>> Everything else after that takes care of
itself.
>> Yeah.
>> Most people don't do that. They say I
have this great idea for who? It's not a
great idea for everyone. That's a given.
So who is it for? When you focus on an
audience so much, do you then maybe risk
the danger of getting the audience
wrong?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. This isn't for amateurs. This is
hard. And I I mean, I've done it wrong
so many times. I've failed more than
most people. the beginning of my career
when I was selling books as a book
packager, I assumed that the audience
were business people at book publishers
because I wanted them to give me
$100,000 for me to make a book. They're
business people. That's what business
people do. So, I brought spreadsheets
and I wore a suit and I brought market
analysis and in the first year after I
sold my first book, I got 800 rejection
letters in a row. 800 times people in
book publishing said, "We looked at
this, we thought about this." No,
>> I arriving rivaling JK Rowling with that
one.
>> Yeah, it was it was a long slog. And
then I met this guy John Boswell and
John took me to his office and he showed
me that what he was doing was he was
word processing his book proposals. This
is 1987. and then giving them to a
secretary who would type them on a
manual typewriter on onion skin paper
with carbon paper because the story was
he was a real author. He wasn't running
a factory. And what I discovered is when
I went to these underpaid,
underappreciated book editors and said,
"Let's talk together about the human
vision you have for books and not
mention at all whether it's going to
sell." They got excited. And then I was
in business. And I still wanted to make
books that readers wanted to buy, but my
story to publishers wasn't, "Let's make
money for you." My story to them was
this is a book you'd be proud to
publish.
>> So you have to change the way in which
you're going to the audience if it
>> and if you're wrong like if you write a
book called All Marketers Are Liars and
you're trying to get marketers to buy
it, you probably made a mistake and I
did. [laughter]
>> Do do you think the same would be true
for corporate America who might already
have a pre-existing product and already
have a belief system and market
analytics and data behind that?
Businessto business selling is just like
selling to consumers except it's
somebody else's money. All the people
you're you're selling to in a in a
corporate America environment are asking
themselves one question. What will I
tell my boss?
>> If you don't give them a good answer,
they're going to buy the cheap one.
Yeah.
>> Or the one they used to buy.
>> Yeah. But if you can say this is going
to raise your status in the organization
or you're falling behind your
competition or some emotional thing that
they can race to their boss and tell
them that's how you get a sale.
I'm just thinking about
the so focusing so much on the consumer
or the buyer or who you're marketing to.
What if that changes over time based off
of like climate? Like for example, COVID
changed a lot of things. Um, how if
you're hyperfocused on creating your
brand around that original audience, how
do you segue into a new audience when
that changes without seeming inauthentic
or
>> inconsistent? Yes. Uh, it's going to
change. It's not will it, it's going to.
That's why you even have an opportunity
because if it wasn't changing, your
competition would already be fine. It
it's when the systems change that things
occur. So what do we sell? We only sell
maybe four things. We sell status,
affiliation, the freedom from fear, and
convenience. That's it. Status. It's not
just money. It's who eats lunch first.
Status is up and who's down. Hollywood
does not make movies. Hollywood makes
status. And the movies are a souvenir of
their status machine. They don't make
money. They don't make movies seeking to
make the most amount of money. They make
movies to make the most amount of status
for the people who are involved. Okay.
Affiliation. People like us do things
like this. Who's to your left? Who's to
your right? Who are you part of? So, if
we look at those two ones first and we
think about something like Patagonia,
you can get warm way cheaper with
somebody other than Patagonia. Patagonia
began by making small little metal
pythons that would that mountain
climbers would use. There was only
10,000 people in their smallest viable
audience. That's it. And they began by
serving people who self-identified as
dirt bags. And that's not how you build
a multi-billion dollar company. Except
it is because what they stood for status
and affiliation.
>> Freedom of fear involves I don't want to
be left behind. I don't want to die. All
these other things. And convenience, as
Tim Woo has pointed out, is the
extraordinary third rail that once
someone offers convenience, everybody
gives up everything else because we've
been indoctrinated to do that.
>> If you start with that, now you can
shift gears.
>> So, Louis Vuitton, multi multi-billion
dollar company, began by making trunks
by hand for incredibly wealthy European
aristocrats. Now, the last time I
checked, 25% of all the women in Japan
had an a Louis Vuitton handbag. 25%.
Why? They have lots of ways to carry
their stuff, but they don't have an
easier way to get status or affiliation.
>> So, you're saying that if you go into
the brand with the right kind of
strategy, with how you're organizing
things, you can kind of switch gears in
an easier way. even if the um audience
changes in a considerable way.
>> Most great brands don't make a product.
They make a story. And the story is
bigger than the product. Which means
that when the world changes, the story
can probably be applied to a different
solution to a different problem.
I'm still
>> Go ahead. [laughter]
>> I
>> This is a big This is a very big idea
that I got here.
>> So if
if you have
Okay. So say you want to create more
products or or something you want to add
services then that changes your brand
slightly, right? and could increase or
change the audience. How do you switch
gears with that? Because it's still even
though let's pick a specific example
like a famous one like Nike or Apple or
a small little Philadelphia business
like Goldie. What What do you want to
pick? I'll pick anything you want.
>> We'll go we'll go big. We'll go Nike.
>> Okay. So, what is Nike's brand?
>> Nike is sports.
>> If [laughter] N if But there are other
brands there are other brands that do
things like sports like Puma, right? it.
Hyatt is a hotel, right? If Hyatt came
out with a brand of sneakers, we have no
idea what it would be like.
>> Yeah.
>> It would just be boring, but we have no
idea.
>> Maybe they'd be like really comfortable
for hotels, you know?
>> If Nike announced they were going to
open a hotel, we know exactly what it
would be like
>> because Nike has a brand.
>> Hyatt has a logo. Big difference.
>> Yeah.
>> So, Nike shows up and Phil Knight and
his partner use a waffle iron. They make
sneakers for no more than 500 people in
the United States could be their target.
But from the very first day, they stood
for exactly one thing, which is beating
the competition. And there are statues
on the Nike campus, full-size, of people
who have extended themselves. The key to
the Nike legend is he had a deal with
Sears and it was all right, we're
willing to sell Nike and Sears, but you
must never put us in the Sunday Circular
because we our brand doesn't belong
there. And some mid-level person at
Sears made a mistake and they put it in
the Sunday Circular. Nike pulled all
their sneakers from every store
>> and it was a lot of money for Sears.
Sears calls and calls and calls. Phil
won't take their call. So finally they
pull every string they can and they talk
to a receptionist or somebody and they
say if we fly in well she says you can
fly in. So they send two very senior
people to headquarters which is far from
Chicago and Phil has these guys wait in
the lobby for eight and a half hours so
that every single person who worked at
Nike could watch them as they paraded
back and forth and then he sends them
home without even meeting with them
>> because that's what Nike stands for. So
now Nike can sell velour sweatshirts to
couch potatoes. The product has changed
completely, but the story is still the
same story, which is if in your head you
want to feel like an exceptional couch
potato, here's a here's a $19
sweatshirt. So would you recommend if
someone wanted to um maybe um they
already have a brand and they wanted to
create a new product or something that
is wildly different than the initial
one. Would you recommend that they use
that segue strategy or would you
recommend that they just open another
business?
>> A lot of people who think they have a
brand don't have a brand. They have a
product that they care a lot about.
They've said you can pick anyone and
we're anyone that if they disappeared I
just call the next plumber in the phone
book. My plumber doesn't pro the
probably doesn't have a brand. Okay. If
you are visualizing a line of innovative
products it's worth taking a breath and
saying does this keep the same promise
to the same kind of people. If it does,
I can call this watch an Apple Watch
because Apple makes luxury goods for
people who aspire to have good taste
about digital interaction. They don't
make computers. They make that.
>> So, they can extend in a bunch of
interesting directions. They probably
shouldn't come out with snack food
because
>> apples,
>> even if it's
>> apple branded apples.
>> Exactly. [laughter]
>> But it will undermine the position of
the big brand. So lots, you know, so
when I was a book packager, my books
were all over the place. I did books
about gardening. I did the gorilla
marketing books. I did books on um uh
interior design and things, but my brand
to the book publishers was I never miss
a budget. I never miss a deadline. And
I'm a little weird.
So like, if you want the normal thing,
I'm not going to be able to help you.
But those three things you're going to
get from me if I bring you a book.
>> And that's consistency. and to the to
the public. I'd put different authors
names on things. So when when I did a
series of novels about Nintendo games,
my name wasn't on the cover because
nine-year-old boys didn't know who I
was. And so we get to pick who we're
telling the story to and what the story
is.
>> Okay. So would So what you're saying is
and it kind of sounds like you can kind
of strategically
change your brand voice for those
populations because you are technically
your brand, right? So and you have done
many different things with that, but
you're kind of picking different
personas as in um to reflect what you're
selling. Is that what you're saying?
>> Yeah. Well, once I became the logo of
the brand, you know, the face and the
other, now my options are more limited.
>> So, uh, I wrote a book about, uh,
mimedics and evolution. I had Charles
Darwin write the forward, which is not
easy because he's dead. And it took a
year of my life to create. I worked
harder on that book than any other book.
>> And it was a bomb. It got me kicked out
of publishing. It didn't work because my
brand at the time stood for this is the
marketing guy and all of a sudden here's
a book about evolution. I would get up
to give a talk and I would just watch
people's eyes instantly glaze over
because most people in the population
don't want to talk about evolution.
>> It makes them nervous. They don't
understand it. They don't want to learn
more about it. They're done.
>> Scared.
>> And I was like, "Okay, now I have a
choice. I can become uh the person who's
just going to keep writing books that
interest me and watch my sales go lower
and lower and lower. Or I could say,
what do the people who trust me want
from me? How can I expand
that area that I'm talking to them about
without going too far outside the
Overton window? Because if you do that,
it breaks. I would say most most people
may not be as adventurous or willing to
fail as much as you have. Uh what would
you say to those people that may not
have that have that anxiety of of
actually failing um and being able to
get back up as as many and often as you
have?
>> Yeah. Well, it and I totally feel them.
It's not easy. But just saying it that
clearly is why
>> you're frustrated and having trouble
because you're afraid to fail. You're
attached to the outcome. You've walked
away from the practice. You've walked
away from the process. And now you are
failing because you're afraid to fail.
And so what we need to do is make it so
that failure is really cheap. And we
need to make it so that shipping is not
a big piece of drama. So what does that
mean? It means if you want to open a
flower store, do not shut down your
career as a dermatologist and invest
your life savings and open a flower
store. That's too scary. Instead,
get a job on the weekends working four
hours in a flower store. It will cost
you nothing. In fact, they'll pay you to
do that. And then while you're there,
try seven different things to say to
people when they walk in the store. The
worst that'll happen is they'll walk
out. You don't care. It's not even your
store. And now you're starting to become
an expert on what are these interactions
like? You failed and failed and failed
in these tiny ways that no one else is
even seeing. And that's part of the
beauty of my blog. You know, I hit
10,000 posts a few months ago. Half my
blog posts are below average, but I just
don't know which half until after I try.
[laughter]
Do you how long do you recommend that
you
for lack of a better phrasing analyze uh
failure? Because obviously there's
they're always learning moments and like
they're you know you should be thankful
for being able to understand when
something isn't good. Um but I think
that a lot of people struggle with
spending too much time thinking about
their failures and then they don't get
past them.
>> Yeah. So, um, Steve Blank teaches us
this really important lesson called
customer traction. That's all you care
about if you're analyzing a startup.
Customer traction. Do customers come
back and do they come back again? We
want to iterate as fast and as much as
we can to get to customer traction. And
one element of it is out of our control
once we launch, which is the network
effect. Do customers bring us other
customers? Because of attraction, we can
see instantly.
So, uh, one exercise that I challenge
people to do to actually do is to, uh,
grab some $5 bills and go to the bus
station and walk up to somebody and say,
"Uh, sorry to bother you. I need a
dollar bill for that vending machine.
Can I sell you this $5 bill for a
dollar?"
>> It's really hard to do that. M
>> it is really because no one at the bus
station is expecting that an honest
person is going to come up to them and
sell them a $5 bill for a dollar. So you
have no trust. You're interacting with a
stranger. You discover all these things
about it that are hard. And when we
start to it iterate back and forth in
lowcost ways to become expert at what
does our smallest viable audience like?
What do they dream of? We can start to
earn customer traction. and analyzing
what didn't work is not nearly as
important as trying a new thing to see
if that works more than the thing that
didn't work.
>> And that doesn't work if we're talking
about writing a a historical novel that
took four years to write because you
only get to do that once every four
years. But there's so many steps before
that. You could go to a coffee shop or
bookstore and read a chapter out loud
and see what happens. Do people get up
and leave or do they ask for chapter
two? Right? That's the iterative
process.
>> Was was there a time that you became
discouraged by the blog?
>> By the blog
>> because after 10,000 I mean that's
consistency. Correct.
>> The blog is a gift to me.
>> I don't make any money from it. I don't
sell any ads on it. I write it even if
no one reads it.
>> It is this lovely tool I have for two
reasons. one to tell myself a truth
about the future in writing that I can
hold myself to because people don't want
to be a hypocrite and two because I get
to whisper to some people who want to
hear what I have to say. What a
privilege that is.
>> Yeah.
>> So I don't use it as a tool. If I used
it as a tool for corporate growth, it
would frustrate me all the time. But
that's not what I think a blog is for.
>> Yeah. It seems like you have a good
relationship with all the things that
you do. Is there um
I kind of want to expand upon that like
do you do you feel like you actually
have relationships with the different
types of products or the types of things
that you more or less sell books uh
speaking uh the blog whatever else it
may be like I guess I'm it's a self-s
serving question in a sense that at
times when I'm creating I always have an
objective in mind and the objective is
so large that I then therefore get
discouraged encourage
>> uh and then I am paralyzed.
>> Yeah.
>> I I stop doing it. Then I go to chat GPT
and and I ask for a little bit of help
and then it helps me and then I go, "Oh
man, I didn't didn't hit that million
dollar, you know, whatever that million
views that I was looking for." Like, how
do you how are you able mentally to be
able to to place all these things in
different silos or or relationships
within your own brain?
>> I'll do my best. I want to make sure I'm
getting clear about this. But first, I'm
a bad example because I'm spoiled,
right? My life is an art project. And
most people aren't going to be lucky
enough to have their life be an art
project.
>> But when I was traveling to speak, you
know, I would give a talk for free.
You're paying all that money for the
eight hours I had to spend getting to
you, right? Because I hate that part of
it, being away and being jetlled and
getting sick. That's why I want to make
sure someone's going to pay a lot
because I'm not going to come all that
way if they're not serious.
But most people don't get that. Most
people have to have a job and it's
nothing they would be doing as a hobby.
It's a job. So my dad and now my sister
um a hospital crib factory make most of
the hospital cribs in the United States.
>> Hospital cribs intellectually is about a
three-hour problem. And once you
understand how hospital cribs are made,
etc., it's it's wonderful because you're
saving the lives of small kids, but the
crib itself is a solved problem. So my
job when I contributed there was to say,
all right, how can I look at this system
of hospitals and nurses and how are
people making decisions to help this
thing grow? That's not Seth on stage. No
one knows I'm touching this. This is a
job, right? And for me, the motivation
is, is there an interesting gap in the
system? Is there an interesting story to
tell? Is there a problem to solve, a key
that's going to open a lock? I can do
that all day long. Yeah.
>> And the only reason I do that with my
face as the logo is because I don't have
to debate it with anybody. I own my
face, so I get to do whatever I want.
But most of the time you have this
tension which is I got to persuade the
client or I got to persuade my peers
that we're going to take the brand we
have and solve an interesting problem
with it. And I've been to major major
brands and public figures with
interesting solutions and most of the
time they're like we're afraid.
>> It's okay.
>> What is your process with um looking at
a problem creatively? cuz I think that a
lot of people are always concerned with
being like the right solution or the
most unique solution that stands out,
but it's not always easy to get to that
point or feel that you're doing it.
>> Yeah. So, let's talk about systems.
We're not under the circumstances. We
are the circumstances. And we're not
stuck in traffic. We are traffic.
There are systems all around us. and
they're they're hiding in plain sight
because systems like to hide so they can
stick around. So, for example, uh if
your daughter when she's seven gets a a
C on a report card, you and your partner
will be stressed. Why? She's never going
to make a living doing fractions, right?
The fact that she didn't do well on
fractions shouldn't bother you, but it
does. And the reason it does is because
450 years ago, Harvard University
started this path to the college
industrial complex. And one of the
prizes the college industrial complex
offers good parents of means is you have
to put a sticker on your car when your
kid is 18. And that's proof that you
were a good parent. And so when they're
seven, it begins.
>> Sure.
>> Right. And so the system runs really
deep. And you you run into teenagers and
they say, "I'm going to go to a good
college." No, you want to go to a famous
college. So, those are different things,
but you've been brainwashed into that.
So, we're talking near Halloween, and I
brought this. This is a a cacao bean.
It's not really a bean. It's a piece of
fruit. And inside of it are all the
little beans that they make chocolate
from. This is a system. In the United
States, billions and billions of dollars
are spent just on cheap chocolate for
Halloween. And that's normal. You have
to serve something to the hoodlims who
come and ring your doorbell or they'll
egg your house. It's part [laughter] of
the system. You have to use a famous
brand because kids have been trained not
to want to eat, you know, the licorice
juju bees or whatever it is. It's got to
be a fun size pack. The chocolate
companies have shareholders. They have
to make the maximum amount of short-term
profit. They have scientists who have
figured out how to make reliable
commodity chocolate. So they don't have
to rely on uh talented people to grow
the chocolate. And in fact, they use a
kind of tree that is hearty but makes
chocolate that tastes worse. And that
tree tends to grow in Ghana and the
Ivory Coast where people can be pushed
to work as cheap as possible. And in
fact, many of them are children in slave
or indentured servant conditions. And if
you tell that to somebody when they're
at the supermarket about to buy cheap
chocolate, they're like, "Yeah, I
probably don't want to participate in
enslaving small children, but we do."
>> Sure.
>> Because of the system.
>> And so if you want us come up with
interesting, useful ideas, you look see
where is there a system and where is
there a flaw in the system where I can
begin to make a change happen. So Sal
Khan sees the college industrial complex
and he invents the Khan Academy. And now
more people have learned more stuff from
the Khan Academy than any college in
history.
>> Right? Or Sean Esenoszi sees this and
says, "I'm going to do direct trade. I'm
going to work directly with the farmers.
I'm going to pay them five times the
minimum wage. I'm going to have open
book management." And on and on and on.
He doesn't have a billion dollar
company, but he has a company that
others are copying because he raises the
standard. And once you see the system
and the challenge of the system, now you
have a place to go solve a problem
>> using because this event is primarily
AIdriven or at least the disruption of
of AI specifically.
Do you find that it's exponentially
harder, easier, the same using AI in
order to help you understand what that
potential problem is? And then if so,
once you find it, you know, how do you
make it grow?
>> Yeah. So, it's 300 times easier, maybe
400 times easier. And it's scarier
because there's nothing to slow you
down. So, if you can begin by having a
conversation with Claude about a system,
there's a woman named Danella Meadows.
She passed away too young. Danella wrote
the groundbreaking book about systems.
So, begin by saying, using the mindset
of Danella Meadows,
>> please explain this system to me.
Okay, now please explain who this system
isn't serving. Now let's dive into this
and and so within two and a half hours
you've generated a month's worth of
insight. Okay, now what? Well, more and
more companies are easier to start with
fewer and fewer people, sometimes no
people. So what will it take to get the
minimum viable product for the smallest
viable audience to see if you get
customer traction? Not nearly what it
used to take, right? So it used to take
me a year when I was a book packager or
more to bring a book to the world. The
Stanley Kaplan test prep books I did
took seven years. Now between AI and the
Kindle, I can have an idea on Monday and
bring it to the market on Wednesday.
So if something gets traction, then I
can do more of it.
So, what we have is this chance if we
want to make slop
or to take a deep breath and say, "I'm
going to make internal slop, but then
I'm going to pick the winners and I'm
going to put my name on it and bring
that into the world." M
>> do you feel that um AI gives more people
opportunities to kind of create and grow
a business based off of um just like new
systems that are cheaper to use like
more accessible um like more resources
are being used? Do you think that
there's going to be this boom of more
creation since it? because I think that
a lot of people are really negative
about AI and fair but um there's there's
many uh reasonable
uh points about that. Um but I think
that a positive way that I've seen is
that there's so many people that have
the opportunity to do things that they
haven't before. Do you agree with that?
>> Yeah. So if you give AI projects, it's
going to give you slop and that's for
the next period of time that's going to
be true. That's why you see slop music
and slop videos and all these people
racing to the bottom with the sloppiest
of slop. Just don't do that because the
problem with racing to the bottom is you
might win. Don't you don't want to be at
the bottom.
>> But if you give it tasks,
then what you can create of value by
doing projects where you put yourself on
the line can go through the roof. So, if
we look at the book business, which I'm
familiar with, they used to publish
50,000 books a year in the United
States, 1,000 books a week. There was a
book shortage because people wanted to
read more than a thousand new books a
week.
>> When the Kindle shows up, the number of
books published in the United States is
now a million a year. It's up by a
factor of 20. Now many of those are
terrible but some of them like you
Howie's books the science fiction
breakthrough books like uh wool are
magnificent which would never have been
possible if he had had to spend a year
to go through the other system. So the
same thing is true when we think about
the the multiplying effect. AI is going
to it's unlikely it's going to invent a
new luxury brand bigger than Hermes,
right? But it's very likely it's going
to invent a uh woodworking tool for the
3,000 people who know what a dado is and
want to do dovetales.
>> Go find that, right? The the hyper
specific. It's going to invent hybrid
seeds that are going to be able to not
GMO, but just oldfashioned hybrid seeds
by mixing this and mixing this that are
going to grow a different sort of thing
in a different neighborhood that we
could never have afforded to do if you
needed to make a seed that would grow
across an entire state.
These are all going to be built and you
want to find one that's not obvious,
that's not easy, that's worth your time.
And then you iterate and iterate and
iterate until you're ready to put your
name on it.
>> Can you talk about an example because
you actually brought some to us today, I
believe, um of a way in which um AI or
an AI tool has been able to help you
create something that you didn't
originally think would be possible or
lucrative.
>> Yeah. So, I um I discovered when
Photoshop went from version three to
version 4 that if I wasn't willing to be
bad at it for many hours, I was going to
fall off. I've never caught up to
Photoshop ever since. I still used the
same tools from the first version. I
don't know what an alpha channel is.
It's like I didn't fail enough. And so,
I gave up on that tool. So, when AI
showed up, I was like, "This is giving
me a headache. I'm not great at it. And
if I just wait, I'm always going to be
behind. How do I sign up to build the
thing that I'm going to ship to the
public using AI in a way I'm proud of?
And I entered a fugue state and didn't
come out of my office for five weeks.
And in those five weeks, I built, I
programmed, I designed, I organized, and
I illustrated three decks of cards,
which we then launched as a Kickstarter.
and we did 5x the goal. And these cards,
I've seen people use them. It's
mind-blowing what happens. So, the the
one that seems to be the most popular is
the Divination Tarot deck. So, on one
side are [snorts] 50 really cool tarot
like images, but much more modern. You
play four of them and then you turn one
over. And on the other one, they turn
over. There's a QR code. Scan the QR
code. It opens an artifact that I
programmed with Claude. type in the
names of the other three uh tarot cards
and it will use one of 50 different
modalities like anagram, Freud, tarot,
numerology, cabala, and give you a
reading, a positive open-ended reading.
And now you can talk to it for as long
as you want about what you just learned.
It's not going to change the world, but
I learned a ton making it and the people
who touch it want to use it again. So
yeah, there you go. that would have
never existed as recently as nine months
ago. You couldn't do that. the question
that I'm thinking like when you're
talking I'm thinking and I see all of
these amazing things that you're doing
and it and and it ultimately leads to
legacy and I I don't necessarily know if
you have like an affiliate or a strong
connotation affiliation to that word
specifically
but has the chapters of your book your
life story has that changed from the
original foundations of blog one to blog
10,000 us.
Um I was a struggling entrepreneur for a
very long time close to bankruptcy for
many years and when that's going on and
the alternative is you got to get a job
as a bank teller it really focuses on
one thing right so during that period of
my life it was like it's got to be work
I'm proud of but it also has to pay the
bills I got to get above water on this
>> so I did email addresses of the rich and
famous which was in odd book to be proud
of, but I thought it was clever. Um, and
we did books and projects that I was
proud of, but we were very focused on
not drowning. And then I started one of
the first internet companies. And after
that, I could take a breath and say,
"All right, now what's the art project?
What is the change I seek to make?" And
my friend Simon, his book about why is
brilliant, but I don't think you need to
wait for your purpose. I think you make
the work you do your purpose, not the
other way around. And so what I chose to
do as I was walking into the uh century
of the 2000s is I measure what do the
people I taught teach other people.
>> If I can create that cycle of teaching
people things that I think make the
world better, that they teach other
people, that's good day. Yeah. Do you
feel like um there's always this
conversation of like especially
entrepreneurs nowadays
um side hustles are the cool thing. Um
do you feel like
entrepreneurship or at least creativity,
storytelling, can that be taught or is
that just something innately within you?
Some things are talents. Dunking a
basketball is one of them. If you're not
born tall, you're not going to be able
to do it. Most things are skills. We can
learn to be more charismatic, funnier,
uh a better leader. We can learn these
things. If you can learn them, they're
skills. There's zero doubt in my mind,
zero, that entrepreneurship is a skill.
I have taught it to people. I've taught
it to people. If you are enrolled in the
journey, if you're committed to the
change, you can learn how to do this.
>> And we got to be very careful about our
words. Entrepreneurship and freelancing
are different things. And proud of one
or the other. Freelancers, and that's
what I am most of the time, get paid
when we work with our own two hands.
Entrepreneurs build something bigger
than themselves. If you're calling
yourself an entrepreneur, you've got to
come to the conclusion that any job you
can describe, you need to hire someone
else to do. That's your job. Larry
Ellison doesn't code at Oracle. His only
job is to hire people to do all the
jobs.
Freelancers, and I've gotten down to a
staff of zero, just me. Freelancers have
a different life. And it's not a life
based on infinity. It's a life based on
did I do valuable work to get me better
clients. If you're a freelancer,
celebrate the great clients. And you do
not become, you do not get better
clients by doing a good job for bad
clients. You get better clients by
becoming the kind of freelancer great
clients want to hire. But own it. Be a
freelancer. You don't have to call
yourself an entrepreneur. If you're an
entrepreneur, you can do it on the side.
That's fine. You don't have to be a
workaholic. But own that and say the
measure of what I'm doing is I'm
building something bigger than myself.
Do you feel that creativity is a talent
or a skill?
>> It's a skill. Skill, skill, skill,
skill, skill. Everything's skill.
>> Every person I know when they were six
used finger paints to paint something
that was original. And when they were
seven, they told a joke at least once
that was funny. So if you can do it
once,
then we try to brains wash it out of
you. But you did it. So, you already
have the ability to do something that
has never been done before. Now, we're
just talking about the degree and I know
some really well-known creative people
and the only thing they have in common
is they decided to be creative.
>> It's incredible. I I think as we're
closing this uh this incredible journey
and this incredible interview
conversation,
um I'm kind of we've painted a picture.
I say relatively good picture today and
I would love to be able to know from
your life's work. You said if you if you
were to rewrite the uh business please
almond act um and it would say go look
it up.
>> Yeah. [laughter] Yeah. Um is there a
particular painting or picture in mind
that your work as a freelancer and
entrepreneur maybe what that would look
like?
>> [laughter]
>> This is a great great question. [snorts]
Okay, so we're in Philadelphia. That's
got to be where the answer comes from.
um Baroness Elsa von Fry Tag Loring
Hovven who was the original punk artist
and she was also a Baroness and she
lived down the hall from Marcel Duchamp
and she was friends with some famous
photographers as well and Marcel Duchamp
uh as a joke took a piece of her work
had it photographed signed it our mut
and entered it into an art exhibit under
his own oposes. Because Baroness was a
woman, it wouldn't have gotten in.
>> And this piece of art called fountain is
a urinal that is just hanging on the
wall of the museum.
Over the years, as Duchamp dealt with
writer's block, which is made up, and
played chess all the time, he kept
taking more and more credit for
inventing it. And the Baroness has never
gotten sufficient credit.
>> And the image is right down the street
here. And if you go, there are some
three other really important Duchamp
pieces right next to it. And Marcel
Duchamp
probably knew how to draw. I have no
idea. It doesn't matter. What he knew
how to do was see the system, see the
system being changed and show up with
something that touched some people, but
not most, in a way that they could never
forget. And so if I'm really really
really being grandiose, I would like to
think that you could put that picture of
the fountain and say he's doing his best
to do that.
>> I think we just have to end it there.
That was perfectly said. And on a
personal level, um, as we end this, um,
your ability to make us feel warm and
comforting and human has been an
absolute honor to be able to just chat
with you for as long as we have. Um, and
out of anybody that we've ever talked
to, u, personally and professionally, I
think you were the one person that made
us feel home. And, uh,
>> thank you so much,
>> and we're forever grateful for that. So
Seth, thank you for your time. It's
>> been fantastic. Good to know both of
you.
>> And thank you for the laughs. I
[laughter] was sleeping.
>> Cool. I think that's it.
>> Go make a ruckus, everybody. Yeah. Yes.
[laughter]
>> Thank you so much.